<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R | Mike Mahoney</title>
    <link>/tags/r/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tags/r/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>R</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Mike Mahoney 2019</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2020 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>R</title>
      <link>/tags/r/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>spacey: Obtain Spatial Data and Make Better Maps</title>
      <link>/project/spacey/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/spacey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;spacey&lt;/code&gt; package provides three main functions to make it easy to
quickly build beautiful maps of locations in the United States via the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/tylermorganwall/rayshader&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;rayshader&lt;/a&gt; package. First
off, it provides an &lt;code&gt;automap&lt;/code&gt; function to quickly make maps using data
from the USGS national map, as well as letting you incorporate overlay textures from ESRI’s
MapServer API and optionally even turn these into 3D visualizations.
All of these can also work with the &lt;code&gt;future&lt;/code&gt; package to speed up
processing, letting you iterate on your map designs faster!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And while &lt;code&gt;automap&lt;/code&gt; tries to make it easy to configure these maps,
&lt;code&gt;spacey&lt;/code&gt; also lets you save off your heightmaps and overlays directly
through the functions &lt;code&gt;get_heightmap&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;get_overlay&lt;/code&gt;, so that you can
work directly with &lt;code&gt;rayshader&lt;/code&gt; to make these maps by yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot more to these three functions, alongside a few basic
geospatial utilities &lt;code&gt;spacey&lt;/code&gt; implements to make it easier to make maps
from your data. For more information, check out the &lt;a href=&#34;https://mikemahoney218.github.io/spacey/articles/introduction-to-spacey.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;introductory
vignette&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find more information about this project in the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://mikemahoney218.github.io/spacey/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt;, or check out the
code on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mikemahoney218/spacey&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Announcing {spacey}, now on CRAN!</title>
      <link>/post/spaceycran/spacey-release/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/spaceycran/spacey-release/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;I’ve launched a new package to CRAN! &lt;code&gt;spacey&lt;/code&gt; helps you pull elevation and
image overlay data from the USGS and ESRI, then helps you turn them into
beautiful maps via &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rayshader.com/&#34;&gt;the fantastic &lt;code&gt;rayshader&lt;/code&gt; package&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The package has a &lt;a href=&#34;https://mikemahoney218.github.io/spacey/&#34;&gt;documentation website&lt;/a&gt;
built with &lt;a href=&#34;https://pkgdown.r-lib.org/&#34;&gt;pkgdown&lt;/a&gt; – check it out for more
information!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Announcing {heddlr}, now on CRAN!</title>
      <link>/post/heddlrcran/heddlr-release/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/heddlrcran/heddlr-release/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;My first package just got published to CRAN today! &lt;code&gt;heddlr&lt;/code&gt; is a set of tools
that make it easier to write modular R Markdown documents by decomposing them
into a set of patterns which can be repeated and combined based on your input
data, letting you dynamically add and remove sections based on your data. I
started this package to solve an issue I found myself running into when
building &lt;a href=&#34;https://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/flexdashboard/&#34;&gt;flexdashboards&lt;/a&gt;, and
have since found out that there’s all sorts of cool tricks you can do by
applying this type of functional programming mindset to R Markdown documents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find out more on heddlr’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://mikemahoney218.github.io/heddlr/&#34;&gt;documentation website&lt;/a&gt;,
proudly made in R via &lt;a href=&#34;https://pkgdown.r-lib.org/&#34;&gt;pkgdown&lt;/a&gt;. This first version
on CRAN is 0.5.0, with 0.1 -&amp;gt; 0.4 previously released on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mikemahoney218/heddlr&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>heddlr: Dynamic R Markdown Document Generation</title>
      <link>/project/heddlr/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 May 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/heddlr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rstudio/rmarkdown&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;R Markdown&lt;/a&gt; is one of the coolest
parts of the R ecosystem, making it trivial to create professional-looking
HTML and PDF documents using simple markdown language. &lt;code&gt;heddlr&lt;/code&gt; looks to
extend that functionality by making it easier to dynamically piece
together documents by intelligently using your data to combine defined
components into a cohesive whole, leading to cleaner code and faster
creation of reports that have many repeating pieces or dashboards which
need to respond to changes in their data sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find more information about this project in the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://mikemahoney218.github.io/heddlr/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt;, or check out the
code on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mikemahoney218/heddlr&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Data Exploration and Analysis with R</title>
      <link>/project/idear/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 May 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/idear/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of resources online to learn R. Some of them are extremely well-written and well-structured, but approach things from a different perspective than I find useful. Some of them are expansive and touch on a massive number of topics, but either don’t go as thoroughly into these topics as might be helpful, or have an interesting writing style or are otherwise hard to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve got a very specific idea of how R should be taught, at least to those interested in using it for data science and other analytical applications. And so in 2018 I began working on a reader - conceived at the time as a series of lecture notes, to support a 3-credit undergrad course - that could be used to learn R that way. However, as I started giving out copies of the reader to friends for feedback, I noticed that a lot of them found the book useful to learn R on their own, and would rather learn that way than in a lecture environment. As such, I started shifting the content into more of a standalone book, attempting to teach R for use in analysis work in both scientific and business contexts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book is currently going through a second round of edits, and may be found in its current state &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/mikemahoney218/IDEAR/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;at this link&lt;/a&gt;. If you find the book helpful (or if you&amp;rsquo;ve got suggestions on how it could be improved), please drop me a line - I love hearing from people who have stumbled across it!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
