<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>data-analytics | Mike Mahoney</title>
    <link>https://www.mikemahoney218.com/tags/data-analytics/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://www.mikemahoney218.com/tags/data-analytics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>data-analytics</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Mike Mahoney 2019</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 18 May 2019 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://www.mikemahoney218.com/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>data-analytics</title>
      <link>https://www.mikemahoney218.com/tags/data-analytics/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Data Exploration and Analysis with R</title>
      <link>https://www.mikemahoney218.com/project/idear/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 May 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.mikemahoney218.com/project/idear/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of resources online to learn R. Some of them are extremely well-written and well-structured, but approach things from a different perspective than I find useful. Some of them are expansive and touch on a massive number of topics, but either don’t go as thoroughly into these topics as might be helpful, or have an interesting writing style or are otherwise hard to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve got a very specific idea of how R should be taught, at least to those interested in using it for data science and other analytical applications. And so in 2018 I began working on a reader - conceived at the time as a series of lecture notes, to support a 3-credit undergrad course - that could be used to learn R that way. However, as I started giving out copies of the reader to friends for feedback, I noticed that a lot of them found the book useful to learn R on their own, and would rather learn that way than in a lecture environment. As such, I started shifting the content into more of a standalone book, attempting to teach R for use in analysis work in both scientific and business contexts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book is currently going through a second round of edits, and may be found in its current state &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/mikemahoney218/IDEAR/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;at this link&lt;/a&gt;. If you find the book helpful (or if you&amp;rsquo;ve got suggestions on how it could be improved), please drop me a line - I love hearing from people who have stumbled across it!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
