<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Mike Mahoney</title>
    <link>https://www.mikemahoney218.com/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://www.mikemahoney218.com/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2019</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 18 May 2019 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://www.mikemahoney218.com/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://www.mikemahoney218.com/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Data Exploration and Analysis with R</title>
      <link>https://www.mikemahoney218.com/project/idear/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 May 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.mikemahoney218.com/project/idear/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of resources online to learn R. Some of them are extremely well-written and well-structured, but approach things from a different perspective than I find useful. Some of them are expansive and touch on a massive number of topics, but either don’t go as thoroughly into these topics as might be helpful, or have an interesting writing style or are otherwise hard to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve got a very specific idea of how R should be taught, at least to those interested in using it for data science and other analytical applications. And so in 2018 I began working on a reader - conceived at the time as a series of lecture notes, to support a 3-credit undergrad course - that could be used to learn R that way. However, as I started giving out copies of the reader to friends for feedback, I noticed that a lot of them found the book useful to learn R on their own, and would rather learn that way than in a lecture environment. As such, I started shifting the content into more of a standalone book, attempting to teach R for use in analysis work in both scientific and business contexts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book is currently going through a second round of edits, and may be found in its current state &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/mikemahoney218/IDEAR/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;at this link&lt;/a&gt;. If you find the book helpful (or if you&amp;rsquo;ve got suggestions on how it could be improved), please drop me a line - I love hearing from people who have stumbled across it!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Impacts of Beaver on Forest Structure and Composition</title>
      <link>https://www.mikemahoney218.com/project/beaverimpacts/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.mikemahoney218.com/project/beaverimpacts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The widespread reforestation of the Northeastern United States has been accompanied by a reintroduction of beaver (Castor canadensis) throughout the region, resulting in profound changes to stream and meadow ecosystems. In contrast to the large body of research on beaver biology and their wetlands, impacts to the adjacent forest from these &amp;lsquo;ecosystem engineers&amp;rsquo; are poorly understood. We are studying the dynamic relationship between landscape drivers of long-term site use by beavers and their reciprocal influence on forest communities adjacent to their ponds.  At a SUNY-ESF research forest in the Adirondack Mountains of New York State, we are using a 30-year record of beaver lodge occupancy to (1) test a process-based model of landscape controls on the duration of beaver occupancy; and (2) quantify the spatially-varying impacts of beaver foraging on forest tree composition and structure. This research will help to better understand the widespread and long-term effects on forests from a keystone species that is increasing in influence throughout North American and Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My current focus is on expanding work done on beaver impacts within the Huntington Wildlife Forest (HWF) to public lands throughout the Adirondacks, to see if the results from our small-scale study at the HWF are applicable to the greater Park. This research may have truly exciting implications for land management moving forward - adaptive management of beaver recolonization has promising applications in wetlands restoration, endangered species recovery, and ecosystem remediation, just to name a few areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in seeing an interactive map of my field sites, &lt;a href=&#34;{{ref &amp;quot;/beaversites/index.html&amp;quot;}}&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;click here!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collaborators:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stacy McNulty (SUNY-ESF)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jacqueline Frair (SUNY-ESF)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Joe Wheaton (Utah State University)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Selected Presentations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Links lead to posters or slides for that presentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mahoney, M. J.&lt;/strong&gt;, and Stella, J. C. (2018). Beaver Foraging Preferences and Impacts on Forest Structure in the Adirondack Mountains of New York. Contributed talk at the Forest Ecosystem Monitoring Collective Conference, Burlington, VT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mahoney, M. J.&lt;/strong&gt;, and Stella, J. C. (2018). Beaver Foraging Preferences and Impacts on Forest Structure in the Adirondack Mountains of New York. Contributed talk at the Rochester Academy of Sciences Fall Scientific Paper Session, Geneseo, NY.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mahoney, M. J.&lt;/strong&gt;, Zevin, R., and Stella, J.C. (2018). Impacts of Beaver on Forest Structure and Composition. Poster session presented at the Spotlight on Student Research, Syracuse, NY.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mikemahoney218.com/project/beaverimpacts/SpotlightPoster2018.png&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;[Poster]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Impacts of Fertilization on Beech Bark Disease</title>
      <link>https://www.mikemahoney218.com/project/beechbark/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.mikemahoney218.com/project/beechbark/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Although beech bark disease was first detected in North America almost 130 years ago, questions remain about this stand-restructuring pathosystem. Two phloem-feeding beech scale insects, &lt;em&gt;Cryptococcus fagisuga&lt;/em&gt;, an invasive species and &lt;em&gt;Xylococcus betulae&lt;/em&gt;, a native species, predispose American beech (&lt;em&gt;Fagus grandifolia&lt;/em&gt;) to infection by &lt;em&gt;Neonectria ditissima&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;N. faginata&lt;/em&gt;, fungal pathogens believed to be a cause of beech decline. While it is known that high bark N:P predisposes trees to BBD, it is unknown whether N or P affects which of the causal organisms are involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the Multiple Element Limitation in Northern Hardwood Ecosystem project (MELNHE), experimental plots have been established within Bartlett Experimental Forest in Bartlett, New Hampshire in order to investigate the impact of nutrient additions on this pathosystem. These plots – located within nine stands of three distinct age classes – have been maintained as controls or fertilized each year since 2011 with either nitrogen, phosphorous, or a combination of both nitrogen and phosphorous. Fungal samples and photographs were collected from these experimental plots in summer and fall of 2017. By quantifying the densities of scale insect and the relative proportions of Neonectria species across plots of different treatments, we hope to understand how nutrient additions impact the causal organisms of beech bark disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Selected Presentations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Links lead to posters or slides for that presentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dillon, G., &lt;strong&gt;Mahoney, M. J.&lt;/strong&gt;, Chase, S., and Johnston, M. (2019). Nutritional Impacts on Invasive Beech Scale Quantification in Beech Bark Disease Aftermath Forests. Poster session presented at the New York Society of American Foresters Annual Meeting, Syracuse, NY.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mahoney, M. J.&lt;/strong&gt;, Leimanis, V., Desrochers, M. L., Giambona, B., Johnston, M. T., Yanai, R. D., and Dillon, G. A. (2018) Impacts of Fertilization on Causal Organisms of Beech Bark Disease. Poster session presented at the Spotlight on Student Research, Syracuse, NY. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mikemahoney218.com/project/beechbark/SpotlightPoster2018.png&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;[Poster]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lasser, G. A., Johnston, M., &lt;strong&gt;Mahoney, M.&lt;/strong&gt;, Leimanis, V., and Stoodley, J. (2017). An Investigation of Nutritional Effects on Beech Bark Disease Causal Organisms. Poster session presented at the Forest Ecosystem Monitoring Collective Conference, Burlington, VT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lasser, G. A., Johnston, M., &lt;strong&gt;Mahoney, M.&lt;/strong&gt;, Leimanis, V., and Stoodley, J. (2017). An Investigation of Nutritional Effects on Beech Bark Disease Causal Organisms. Poster session presented at the Rochester Academy of Sciences Fall Scientific Paper Session, Rochester, NY.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
